Hi. This is Matt Baker. Last month we launched our
Expanded Tree of Life Project, which is going to
result in five brand new taxonomy charts. So far,
I’ve completed Plants & Fungi as well as Birds;
and currently I’m working on the mammal chart,
which is what I’m going to show you today. One
of the great things about this project is that
you have the opportunity to contribute to it
by watching this video and pointing out things
that I missed or got wrong. We received lots of
comments on the bird video and your suggestions
ended up having a major impact on the final
design of that chart so I’m hoping something
similar is going to happen with this one.
Now, as a reminder, you can pre-order any
or all of the new taxonomy charts right now,
by using Kickstarter. While the initial
funding period for the project has now ended,
late pledges are still being accepted
(and will be until the end of October).
So if you’re interested in receiving your charts
in time for the holidays, be sure to head over
to UsefulCharts.com/Kickstarter or simply use
the link in the description or pinned comment.
So, the one thing that all mammals have
in common is that they all have mammary
glands (which allows females to produce
milk for their offspring). However,
not all mammals give birth to live babies. A few
species—such as the playtypus and the echidnas
(both in the Monotremata Order)—actually lay eggs,
just like birds and reptiles do. However, the vast
majority of mammals are in fact livebearers
and they belong to a subclass called Theria,
which simply means “beasts”. From here, things
go in two very different directions. There
are the marsupials, who have a very short
gestation period, after which their babies
continue to develop in an external pouch; and
the placentals, who have a much longer gestation
period (because they have placentas and are
thus able feed their babies in the womb).
Let’s start with the marsupials (which are
shown in purple) as they are the smaller of
the two groups. Now, take note, I’m not going
to be pointing out everything as this is just
a draft version of the chart and I’ll be doing a
more in-depth video sometime next year. But I am
going to hit all of the highlights so that you
can tell me if I missed anything important. Now,
although most marsupials live in Australia,
there are two types that live in the Americas:
opposums and shrew opposums (each of which
are placed in their own orders). By the way,
that number shown below each order name represents
the total number of species in that order. Now,
all of the remaining marsupials belong
to the Australidelphia superorder,
which is made up of 5 orders; although most of
the familiar species are found in Diprotodontia,
such as koalas, wallabies, kangaroos,
the ever so cute quokkas, and wombats.
The only well known Australian marsupial that
doesn’t belong to this order is the Tasmanian
devil, which is in Dasyuromorphia, along
with the recently extinct Tasmanian tiger.
Moving over to the placentals, you'll notice that
things immediately split again in two directions.
This is because, during the early days of mammal
evolution, there were only two main continents on
earth: a northern one and a southern one.
Placentals that trace their origin to the
northern continent are placed in Boreoeutheria
(boreo meaning northern) whereas those that
trace their origin to the southern continent are
placed in Atlantogenata (atlanto being a reference
to the Atlantic ocean—which first formed when the
southern continent broke in two). The western half
of that continent became South America; whereas
the eastern half became Africa—which is why we
get yet another split here. The South American
branch is called Xenarthra, which means “strange
joints” and it is so-named because the animals in
this clade have extra joints in their backbones.
It contains two small orders: the armadillo order
and Pilosa, which includes sloths and anteaters.
Afrotheria is slightly bigger, containing
6 small orders, the most famous of which is
Proboscidea (named after the proboscis—meaning
a long nose or tube). These are, of course,
the elephants, of which there
are only 3 species remaining:
two in Africa and one in Asia. However, take
note that in Afrotheria, we also find hyraxes,
sea cows (such as manatees and dugongs) and
several insectivores (such as the aardvark).
Now, before I continue, I want to mention that
most of the individual images on this chart were
taken from the website iNaturalist (but only from
observations with photos marked public domain).
This video is not sponsored by iNaturalist but
since it’s playing an important role in this
project, I do want to shout it out. Basically,
iNaturalist is for anyone interested in the
natural world, whether they be professionals
or amateurs. This is because it has an app that
anyone can use to identify and make a record of
things observed in nature (such as wild animals,
birds, insects, mushrooms, plants, et cetera).
I’m an active user of the app and if you are too,
you can find me on there as matt hyphen b. I’d
especially appreciate it if you have any photos
you’d like to contribute to the project. Now,
if you haven’t ever used iNaturalist but are
interested in learning more, there’s actually
something coming up called iNat Together where
you find an event near you and show up in person
to explore nature with others and learn how to
use the app. I’ll drop a link in the description
which you can use to search events by location.
There’s even one happening near me, which I’ll
be participating in. So maybe I’ll see you there.
Okay, back to the chart. Let’s now move over to
Boreoeutheria, which is where we find over 85%
of all mammal species. As you can see, things
once again split in two directions. On the left
(shown in green) is Laurasiatheria (Laurasia
being the name of that northern continent I
mentioned earlier) and on the right (shown
in orange and red) is Eu-archonto-glires,
which gets its name because it gets split even
further into Eu-archonta (which means true rulers)
and Glires (which means dormice). Let’s look at
Glires first. It contains the Lagomorphia Order,
which is where we find rabbits and hares; and
the Rodentia Order, which is where we find,
well, rodents. At over 2300 species, the rodent
order is the largest mammal order by far. But
it doesn’t just contain rats and mice. In
this suborder, we get beavers and gophers;
in this one, we get squirrels and their relatives
(such as groundhogs, prairie dogs, and chipmunks);
in this one, we get porcupines, guinea
pigs, and capybaras; and in this one,
we get the ones more closely related to
rats and mice, such as gerbils and hamsters.
Now, when it comes to euarchonta (the “true
rulers”), most belong to the Primate Order
(which means top ranking) however there's also
two smaller orders, the tree shrews and the flying
lemurs. But yeah, it's the Primate Order (shown in
red) which is the main one, with over 500 species
(including humans) so let's take a close look
at them. Primates are first of all divided into
Strepsirrhini (which literally means “wet nosed”)
and Haplorhini (which means simple or dry nosed).
In Strepsirrhini, we get lemurs, lorises, and bush
babies; whereas in Haplorhini we get tarsiers and
simians (simian being a category that includes
both monkeys and apes). But at this point,
things do not divide into monkeys and apes, they
divide into Platyrrhini (which means “flat-nosed”)
and Catarrhini (which means “down-nosed”).
Perhaps more importantly though, Platyrrhini
contains all of the New World simians, whereas
Catarrhini contains all of the Old World simians.
In Platyrrhini, there are no apes but there are
five distinct monkey families, the two main ones
being Cebidae (which includes the capuchins and
squirrel monkeys) and (which includes the spider
monkeys and howlers). In contrast, in Catarrhini,
there is only one monkey family but also two ape
families. The Old World monkey family is called
Cercopithecidae and it includes baboons and
rhesus monkeys, among many others. As for the
apes, there's the gibbon family and then the
“greater ape” family, which is called Hominidae.
Currently, Hominidae consists of eight species,
divided amongst four genera. There's Homo
(which is us), Pan (which is the chimpanzees
and bonobos), Gorilla (which is the two gorilla
species—eastern and western), and Pongo (which
is the three orangutan species, one of which,
P. tapanuliensis, was only discovered in the
late 90s). Now, because this particular family is
so important to us (because, well, we're in it),
there's obviously been a lot of research done
on its evolutionary history. For example,
when it comes to extinct species, there's around
20 more species that could be added. However,
since this particular chart is mostly focused
only on living species, I opted not to go down
that road. Sure, I have included a few extinct
species on this chart but they are all ones that
have gone extinct during the historical
era, as opposed to pre-historical times.
Alright, so that takes care of everything
in Euarchontaglires, which means that it's
now time to move over to the Laurasiatheria
side, which starts in green. Right of the bat,
the Eulipotyphla Order splits off with
everything else being called Scrotifera.
Members of Eulipotyphla (which include
shrews, hedgehogs, and moles) are also
known as true insectivores because they form
the largest group of insect-eaters. In fact,
this order used to be called Insectivora
and it used to include a bunch of other
shrew-like species, which have now (based
on DNA comparison) been placed elsewhere.
Okay, the next order to split off is Chiroptera,
which is where we find bats—the only mammals with
the ability to fly. The bat order is actually
the second largest mammal order, surpassed
only by the rodents. It is used to be divided
into macrobats and microbats but now the terms
Yinptero-chiroptera and Yango-chiroptera are used.
Yinptero-chiroptera includes all of the macrobats
(such as flying foxes) but also a few microbat
families, such as the horseshoe bats and roundleaf
bats. The vast majority of microbats however are
now placed in Yango-chiroptera, with the largest
family being Vespertilionidae (which just means
bats, or more literally, night flyers). The two
most common species found in North America are the
big brown bat and the little brown bat. However,
it is in this family here that we find the famous
vampire bats, who feed exclusively on blood.
Okay, moving up, we come to Ferungulata, so
named because it contains the so-called “wild”
beasts (Ferae) as well as the ungulates
(or hoofed animals). Let’s look at the
ungulates first. They are split into two orders:
Perissodactyla (which literally means odd-toed)
and Artiodactyla (which means even-toed). In
the odd-toed group, we get rhinos, tapirs,
and eequines (which include horses, donkeys, and
zebras). But it’s in the even-toed group that we
get most of the hoofed animals (as well as a bit
of a surprise). First off, there’s the pig family,
as well as the camel family (which not only
includes camels but also llamas and alpacas).
Then we get a group called Cetruminantia (so named
because it combines the prefix Cet- (which means
whale) with the word ruminant. You see, if we go
this way, we come to Whippomorpha, which includes
hippos but also Cetaceans (or whales). So, yeah,
basically, the ancestor of all whales was some
sort of even-toed hoofed animal. Which is why they
are now placed within Artiodactyla instead of in
their own order. However, because they are so
different, I opted to give them a special color.
When it comes to whales, we have two main types:
toothed whales and baleen whales. Basically,
instead of teeth, baleen whales
have a row of fibres called baleens,
which serve a similar purpose.
This group includes grey whales,
humpback whales, and the largest
animals on earth: the blue whales.
In contrast, toothed whales include sperm whales,
belugas & narwals, and all of the dolphins.
Let’s now look at the ruminants, who all
share the trait of chewing their cud,
which is a multiple step process for digesting
food. Ruminants include giraffes but the two
main families are the cervids and the bovids. In
Cervidae, we get deer but also moose, caribou,
and elk; and in Bovidae we get bovines (such as
cows, bison, and buffalos) but also wildebeests,
impalas, gazelles, and caprines
(which include both sheep and goats).
Alright, moving over to the wild beasts.
Basically, everything here belongs to
the Carnivora Order (which I’ve shown in
yellow), except for this small order here,
which includes the pangolins. Carnivora is divided
into the Feliformia (or cat-like) suborder and
the Caniformia (or dog-like) suborder. On the
cat-like side, we get civets, hyenas, mongooses,
and of course, cats. The cat family is called
Felidae and I’ve chosen to show five of 14 felid
genera: Lynx (which is where we find bobcats),
Felis (which is where we find the domestic
cat—represented by one of my own cats, named
Ketsl), Puma (which is where we find cougars,
or mountain lions), Acinonyx (which is where
we find cheetahs), and Panthera (which is where
the find the largest cats). Panthera has a total
of five species and I’ve chosen to show them all:
the jaguar, the tiger, the lion,
the leopard, and the snow leopard.
Finally, let’s look at the dog-like
carnivores. Of course, there’s Canidae,
the main dog family (which includes foxes,
jackals, coyotes, and wolves, from whence came
the domestic dog). But there’s also the pinnipeds
(which include walruses, sea lions, and seals),
the bear family, and the musteloids—which
is where we get skunks, racoons, red pandas,
and the entire Mustelidae Family (which includes
wolverines, badgers, minks, weasels, and otters).
Okay, so that was a look at our brand new
Classification of Mammals chart. Like I say
though, this is just a first draft and I’ll
be making changes based on your comments. So,
if you have any suggestions, do let me
know. And if you want to pre-order the
chart, be sure to click the link in the
description or pinned comment right now.
Thanks for watching.